{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Tacitus recorded that, before this leader’s uprising, a statue of Victory fell down, as if turning its back in retreat. Due to the Roman governor’s absence at Mona, this leader trounced the Ninth Legion and destroyed a temple dedicated to Claudius. Suetonius defeated this ruler’s forces at the Battle of Watling Street. Camulodunum and Londinium were destroyed by an army of Britons led by, for ten points, what British warrior queen of the Iceni?",
      "answer": [
        "Boudica",
        "Boadicea"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Eli Thayer’s New England Emigrant Aid Company attempted to sponsor settlers to move to this territory. Smugglers used crates labeled “books” to bring Henry Ward Beecher’s rifles into this territory. Settlers established towns like Manhattan and Lawrence in this territory, the latter of which was itself sacked by William Quantrill, a bushwhacker crossing from this territory’s eastern neighbor. For ten points, name this territory that was “Bleeding” in the 1850s due to clashes over slavery in towns like Topeka.",
      "answer": "Kansas"
    },
    {
      "question": "One author in this language wrote of a woman whose royal husband communicates with her using a medium after she is killed by soldiers in “The Song of Everlasting Sorrow.” One author in this language wrote of the “rumble-rumble of war chariots” in a poem bemoaning the An Lushan Rebellion. This language was used to write “Drinking Alone By Moonlight” the most noted poem of Li Po. For ten points, name this language in which poets like Bai Juyi and Wang Wei wrote under the Tang Dynasty.",
      "answer": [
        "Middle Chinese",
        "Mandarin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, one side could not move to Gloucester Point due to a storm and could not evacuate at all after the Battle of the Chesapeake. According to legend, ceremonies after this battle featured the losers playing “The World Turned Upside Down.” Redoubts 9 and 10 were captured during this siege, which was led by the Comte de Rochambeau and George Washington against forces under Charles Cornwallis. For ten points, name this decisive battle of the American Revolution at which the British army surrendered.",
      "answer": "Battle or Siege of Yorktown"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event led Governor Martin O’Malley to declare a state of emergency and caused significant damage to an amusement park in Seaside Heights. This event’s coincidence with Halloween season led it to be dubbed a “Frankenstorm,” while some pundits questioned whether it would be an “October surprise” in the Obama/Romney election. Atlantic City casinos were shut down at the behest of Chris Christie during, for ten points, what 2012 hurricane that flooded New York City and much of the Atlantic seaboard?",
      "answer": [
        "Hurricane Sandy",
        "Superstorm Sandy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This battle was preceded by an engagement at Flirey that allowed one side to take control of local railway lines. Fort Vaux and Douamount were heavily contested in this battle. Erich von Falkenhayn was dismissed for failing to win this battle, despite his boast that he would bleed his enemies white. Philippe Petain led French troops to victory in, for ten points, what lengthy 1916 battle for a French fortress city?",
      "answer": "Battle of Verdun"
    },
    {
      "question": "Alexander the Great spared this city after he was shown a prophecy about the fall of the Persian empire. Judas Maccabeus captured this city from the Seleucids, and it was renamed Aelia Capitolina by Hadrian. The Arch of Titus depicts the fall of this city, which the Mount of Olives overlooks. The Crusades sought to retake this city from the Saracens. The Western Wall and the Dome of the Rock are in, for ten points, what Israeli city?",
      "answer": "Jerusalem"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thispositionwastoberevered,andthebarbariansweretobeexpelled,accordingtotheslogan“Sonno Joi.” Scholars and politicians have debated whether the song “Kimigayo” celebrates this figure. Under the Insei, the holder of this position retired to become a Buddhist monk but still held power as a Joko. According to legend, Jimmu was the first holder of this position, whose holders are given a posthumous name reflecting the era in which they ruled. For ten points, what ruler sits on the Chrysanthemum Throne as the leader of an East Asian country?",
      "answer": [
        "Emperor of Japan",
        "Tenno",
        "Mikado"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Bernie Boston was nominated for a Pulitzer Prize for a photo at this location showing a man putting a flower in the barrel of a gun. A set of documents named for this complex were leaked by Daniel Ellsberg and detailed American involvement in Vietnam. A conspiracy theory about this location holds that it was hit by a cruise missile, not an airplane, on September 11th. Arlington County, Virginia is home to, for ten points, what largest office building in the world, the headquarters of the US Department of Defense?",
      "answer": "The Pentagon"
    },
    {
      "question": "A sculpture of this man “Enthroned” was created by Horatio Greenough in the style of Zeus of Olympia. This man was depicted with Commerce, Science, Mechanics, and 13 maidens in his Apotheosis by Constantino Brumidi. This man is the central figure in Grant Wood’s Daughters of the Revolution, and he was depicted in Wood’s painting of Parson Weems’ Fable cutting down a cherry tree. For ten points, name this leader who was depicted crossing the Delaware River.",
      "answer": "George Washington"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This US state was first formally claimed by Commodore John D. Sloat, who became its first military governor. After the city of Sonoma in this state was seized by the forces of William Ide and John C. Fremont, it briefly became its own republic. This site of the Bear Flag Revolt received a massive influx of settlers called “forty-niners” after a valuable commodity was discovered at Sutter’s Mill. For ten points, name this state that underwent a massive gold rush in 1848.",
        "answer": "California"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This businessman arrived in California in 1853 to open a dry goods store, from which he marketed a new invention of one of his customers, riveted denim jeans.",
        "answer": "Levi Strauss"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Members of this religion established a theocratic state in the 2nd century under the “Celestial Masters.” This religion’s ethics focus on an idea sometimes translated “effortless action,” Wu Wei. One thinker from this religion wondered if he was a butterfly dreaming of being a person or vice versa, and was named Zhuangzi [JWANG-tsuh]. For ten points, name this Chinese religion that uses the Yin-Yang symbol and whose central concept is sometimes translated “the way.”",
        "answer": "Daoism or Taoism"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Daoism was founded by this semi-mythical 6th century figure who wrote its central scripture, the Tao Te Ching.",
        "answer": "Laozi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These people used the “blood eagle” execution method, in which the lungs were pulled out of the victim’s chest, on two noblemen according to skaldic poetry. These people inhabited Normandy after a treaty with Charles the Simple. Groups of these people sacked Lindisfarne and demanded ransom from Paris after attacking up the Seine River. One of these people, Leif Erikson, established the Vinland settlement in North America. For ten points, name these Scandinavian raiders.",
        "answer": "Vikings"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The “blood eagle” ritual was describe in the sagas as a sacrifice to this Norse god who hanged himself from Yggdrasil.",
        "answer": "Odin or Wotan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader’s son dismissed pogroms after this leader’s death with the line “when a great tree falls, the earth shakes.” This leader used a slogan translating as “abolish poverty, rescue the country” and launched Operation Blue Star against the Golden Temple at Amritsar, leading to her assassination by her own bodyguards. After her death, this leader’s post was taken by her son, Rajiv. For ten points, name this first female Prime Minister of India.",
        "answer": "Indira Gandhi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Operation Blue Star targeted members of this faith, who were occupying the Golden Temple at Amritsar, this religion’s holiest site. Indira Gandhi’s assassins were members of this fath.",
        "answer": "Sikhism"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this ruler’s coronation, a stampede led to the death of over a thousand people in the Khodynka Field tragedy. This man lost popularity after his forces opened fire on Father Gapon’s supporters outside the Winter Palace. After this ruler abdicated, he and his family were brought to Yekaterinburg, where they were executed in July 1918. The February Revolution ousted, for ten points, what final Tsar of Russia?",
        "answer": "Nicholas II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This daughter of Nicholas II was rumored to have survived the killing of the Romanov family, and imposters like Anna Anderson appeared over the ensuing years claiming to be her. DNA testing has since proven that this girl died in the attack.",
        "answer": "Anastasia Nikolaevna"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A man with this surname created photography’s first glass negative, which featured his father’s reflecting telescope. Another person with this surname embarked on a nighttime ride to deliver news that she discovered her eighth comet with the naked eye; that woman with this surname helped draft Catalogue of Nebulae and Clusters of Stars with her brother, whose Observatory House was equipped with a 40-foot telescope used in his discovery of two of Saturn’s moons. For ten points, name this surname, held by English astronomers Caroline and William, who discovered Uranus.",
        "answer": "Herschel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "When William Herschel discovered Uranus in 1781, he initially named it after this English monarch.",
        "answer": "George III"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Wielbark culture of these people is the subject of Getica, a work by Jordanes. Emperor Valens died fighting these people, who were led by Fritigern, at the Battle of Adrianople. The 410 Sack of Rome was caused by Alaric, a leader of these people. Theodoric the Great led a kingdom of these people in Italy, while another group settled in Spain south of the Franks. For ten points, name this Germanic group that was split into Visi- and Ostro- branches.",
        "answer": [
          "Goths",
          "Visigoths and/or Ostrogoths"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The longest lasting community of the Goths was based in this peninsula, which is surrounded by the Sea of Azov and the Black Sea.",
        "answer": "Crimean Peninsula"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ronald Ebens and Michael Nitz beat a man of this ethnicity to death, but served no time due to a judge who noted, “you make the punishment fit the criminal.” In the 19th century, members of this ethnicity hoped to reach “Gold Mountain” after immigrating to the US; decades later, further immigration was excluded by an 1882 Act targeting these people. For ten points, name this Asian ethnic group that performed much of the labor on the western end of the Transcontinental Railroad.",
        "answer": "Chinese American"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ronald Ebens and Michael Nitz murdered Vincent Chin in this city and were motivated by the fact that this city’s main industry faced opposition from Japanese companies like Mitsubishi.",
        "answer": "Detroit"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Wyoming",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State capital of Wyoming, named for a native tribe attacked in the Sand Creek Massacre.",
          "answer": "Cheyenne"
        },
        {
          "question": "National park primarily located in Wyoming that was established in 1871.",
          "answer": "Yellowstone National Park"
        },
        {
          "question": "Policy that Wyoming was the first state to implement, later implemented nationwide by the 19th Amendment.",
          "answer": [
            "women’s suffrage",
            "descriptions of giving women the right to vote"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "US Vice President under George W. Bush, a Wyoming native.",
          "answer": "Dick Cheney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Industry revolutionized by the use of barbed wire whose workers fought the Johnson County War.",
          "answer": [
            "ranching",
            "anything related to cattle"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of a famous “Wild West Show” and namesake of a Wyoming city.",
          "answer": [
            "William Frederick Cody",
            "Buffalo Bill"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Tribe of Sacagawea; it’s also the namesake of a Wyoming national forest",
          "answer": "Shoshone"
        },
        {
          "question": "First female governor in US history, the successor of her husband, William.",
          "answer": "Nellie Tayloe Ross"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "European Economics",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Common currency adopted by much of the European Union in 2002.",
          "answer": "euro"
        },
        {
          "question": "Energy resource whose English mines were shut down in a 1980s strike that was busted by Margaret Thatcher.",
          "answer": "coal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Food resource that was the subject of Iceland/England territorial disputes, a so-called “War” in the North Atlantic.",
          "answer": [
            "fish",
            "Cod War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Bubbly wine that, by EU law, must come from a namesake region in northern France.",
          "answer": "Champagne"
        },
        {
          "question": "German regime that underwent immense inflation between the World Wars.",
          "answer": "Weimar Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "14th and 15th century league consisting of guilds and towns in northern Europe around the Baltic Sea.",
          "answer": [
            "Hanseatic League",
            "Hansa"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city-state of that league, a Free Imperial City in north Germany.",
          "answer": "Lubeck"
        },
        {
          "question": "Friedrich von Hayek magnum opus, a work that argued that socialism inevitably leads to economic and social oppression.",
          "answer": "The Road to Serfdom or Der Weg zur Knechtschaft"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Australia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern city built on Botany Bay, the site of a famous Opera House.",
          "answer": "Sydney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Australian state that is home to that city, named in part for a member country of the UK.",
          "answer": "New South Wales"
        },
        {
          "question": "TermfornativeAustralians,someofwhomwereabductedfromtheirfamiliesintheStolenGeneration.",
          "answer": "Aborigines or Aboriginal Australians"
        },
        {
          "question": "Precious metal mined by the rebels who built the Eureka Stockade in 1854.",
          "answer": "gold"
        },
        {
          "question": "Flightless birds that “won” a 1932 war against soldiers with machine guns.",
          "answer": [
            "emus",
            "Emu War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Sacred sandstone formation in the Northern Territory where Azaria Chamberlain was killed by a dingo in 1980.",
          "answer": [
            "Uluru",
            "Ayers Rock"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city of the Northern Territory; it was bombed by the Japanese in 1942.",
          "answer": "Darwin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister who was “all the way with LBJ” and mysteriously disappeared while swimming in 1967.",
          "answer": "Harold Holt"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During World War II, this country was led by the military dictator Phibun. This country has been ruled by the Chakri Dynasty since the death of its King Taksin the Great. This country’s monarchs traditionally take the name (20 pts)",
        "“Rama,” and before the founding of this country’s current capital, ruled from cities such as Ayutthaya and (10 pts)",
        "Sukhothai. For ten points, name this Southeast Asian country where a 2004 coup d’etat forced Thaksin Shinawatra out of power in Bangkok."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Thailand",
        "Siam"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Richard of Cornwall and Alfonso X of Castile vied to be leaders of this empire in its interregnum. A leader of this empire expanded into Italy by beating Berengar II and defeated Magyar forces at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Lechfeld. Rules for electing rulers of this empire were decided in the 1356 Golden Bull. Gregory VII excommunicated a ruler of this empire, Henry IV, during the Lay Investiture Controversy. (10 pts)",
        "Charlemagne was the first emperor of, for ten points, what European entity largely centered on medieval Germany and Northern Italy?"
      ],
      "answer": "Holy Roman Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This US state welcomed the von Trapp family singers to its city of Stowe after they fled Austria. This state celebrates an annual holiday on August 16th to commemorate the Battle of Bennington, which was fought in 1777 after it formed a (20 pts)",
        "republic that lasted until it became the fourteenth state in 1791. Lake (10 pts)",
        "Champlain forms part of the western border of this state, which contains the headquarters of Ben & Jerry’s in its city of Burlington. For ten points, name this state that once broke away from its eastern neighbor, New Hampshire."
      ],
      "answer": "Vermont"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Settlements in this modern-day country included one ruled by the tyrant Telys, Sybaris, which was conquered by Croton. Magna Graecia lies in this modern-day country, where the (20 pts)",
        "Pyrrhic War took place. Nicias and Alcibiades led a failed expedition to an island now owned by this country. The (10 pts)",
        "Appian Way lies in this country, the ancient home of the Etruscans. For ten points, name this European country where tourists can visit ruins of the Circus Maximus and Colosseum in Rome."
      ],
      "answer": "Italy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s legacy was maintained largely by his widow, Elizabeth Bacon. Whether this man fathered a child with the captured daughter of Little Rock is a matter of debate, because it is thought that this man became sterile after catching a venereal disease at (20 pts)",
        "West Point, where he graduated at the bottom of his class in 1861. Black Kettle was killed at the Battle of the Washita River by this man’s (10 pts)",
        "7th Cavalry, which was wiped out in 1876 during the Great Sioux [soo] War. For ten points, name this US Army officer whose death at the Battle of the Little Bighorn led it to be known as his “Last Stand.”"
      ],
      "answer": "George Armstrong Custer"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Although lawyers debated whether this man owned a rare pair of Bruno Magli shoes, a photograph that was published in the National Enquirer supposedly showing him wearing the shoes was not entered into evidence. This man, who was arrested after a (20 pts)",
        "sports memorabilia robbery at the Palace Station casino in Las Vegas, was defended by Johnnie (10 pts)",
        "Cochran and Robert Kardashian in an earlier trial concerning the deaths of Ron Goldman and Nicole Brown. For ten points, name this NFL running back who was acquitted of murder in a massive 1995 trial."
      ],
      "answer": "Orenthal James “OJ” Simpson"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician accused the opposing party of “twenty years of treason” in a speech that was analyzed in an episode of See it Now. The Lee List probably inspired a claim by this man that was investigated by the (20 pts)",
        "Tydings Committee. This man attacked the US Army in a series of hearings in (10 pts)",
        "1954 that largely collapsed after Joseph Welch asked this man “Have you no sense of decency, sir?” For ten points, name this US senator from Wisconsin who claimed he had a list of 205 communists in the State Department during the Red Scare."
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph “Joe” McCarthy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This thinker controversially proposed that the inherent value of a commodity consisted of its labor value in a work that criticized what he called “commodity fetishism.” This man theorized an explanation of history in which societies move through an industrial (20 pts)",
        "capitalist stage to a final socialist society. This man declared that “the history of the world is a history of (10 pts)",
        "class struggle” in a work that begins “a spectre is haunting Europe” and was co-written with Friedrich Engels. For ten points, name this author of Das Kapital and co-author of The Communist Manifesto."
      ],
      "answer": "Karl Marx"
    }
  ]
}